We've already explored date functions like date trunc and date part.
لقد استكشفنا بالفعل دوال التاريخ مثل مقطع التاريخ وجزء التاريخ.
In an upcoming lesson,
في درس قادم،
we'll dig into even more functions for getting value from dates.
سنتعمق في مزيد من الدوال للحصول على القيم من التواريخ.
The vast majority of analysis you perform in
الغالبية العظمى من التحليلات التي تقومون بإجرائها في
a professional setting will have dates attached to it,
بيئة احترافية ستتضمن تواريخ مرفقة بها.
but you might not be able to get value out of them,
لكن ربما لن تتمكنوا من الحصول على القيمة منها،
if the dates are not formatted correctly.
إذا لم تكن التواريخ بتنسيق صحيح.
Let's say you've got three separate columns for day,
لنفترض أن لديكم ثلاثة أعمدة منفصلة لليوم
month, and year of a given record.
والشهر والسنة لسجل معين.
Problems like this are common for data that was manipulated in excel at some point,
تعتبر مثل هذه المشاكل شائعة في البيانات التي تمت معالجتها في excel في مرحلة ما،
or exported from a third party system,
أو تم استيرادها من نظام خارجي،
or even data that was just manually entered.
أو حتى الملفات التي أُدخلت يدويًا.
In order to really maximize value here,
لتعظيم القيمة هنا للغاية،
you'll need to convert month names into numbers,
ستحتاجون إلى تحويل أسماء الشهور إلى أرقام،
then concatenate all of these fields together along with hyphens,
ثم ربط كل هذه الحقول معًا بالواصلات،
and then tell the database to understand that the resulting output is a date,
بعد ذلك، عليكم إخبار قاعدة البيانات بأن تفهم أن الناتج عبارة عن تاريخ،
which you can do by using the cast function.
وهذا ما يمكنكم فعله باستخدام دالة التحويل.
Let's tackle the first couple steps of this first.
دعونا في البداية نتناول أول خطوتين.
This first step converted month names into numbers.
الخطوة الأولى هي تحويل أسماء الشهور إلى أرقام.
As you can see, January comes out as one.
كما ترون، يُشار إلى شهر يناير بواحد.
Now let's concatenate that value together with the year and
الآن دعونا نربط تلك القيمة مع السنة
the day to create something that looks like a real date.
واليوم لإنشاء شيئًا ما يشبه التاريخ الحقيقي.
For the last step, we'll cast this new field as a date format.
بالنسبة للخطوة الأخيرة، سنحول هذا الحقل الجديد باعتباره تنسيق التاريخ.
You can see here that the database now understands this as a date and has attached
يمكنكم هنا ملاحظة أن قاعدة البيانات الآن تفهم هذا كتاريخ وقد ألحقت
the appropriate zeros to these records so that it reads properly.
الأصفار الملائمة لهذه السجلات حتى تقرأ بطريقة صحيحة.
The cast function can be a little tricky to read,
من الممكن أن تكون قراءة دالة التحويل أمرًا صعبًا بعض الشيء في البداية.
but luckily, there's also a shorthand.
لكن لحسن الحظ، يوجد أيضًا الاختزال.
Rather than wrapping all of this in a cast function,
بدلًا من تغليف كل هذا في دالة التحويل،
we can simply add two colons and then the data type we'd like to cast at
يمكننا ببساطة إضافة نقطتين ثم نوع البيانات التي نرغب في تحويلها في
the end of this section.
نهاية هذا القسم.
The cast function is most useful for turning strings into numbers or dates.
تعتبر دالة التحويل مفيدة للغاية في تحويل السلاسل إلى أرقام أو تواريخ.
Typically, if you want to turn a number into a string,
وعادة، إذا أردتم تحويل رقم إلى سلسلة،
performing any type of string operation on it like left, right,
فإن إجراء أي نوع من عمليات السلاسل عليها مثل اليسار أو اليمين
or substring will automatically cast the data while performing the operation.
أو السلسلة الفرعية سيحول البيانات تلقائيا أثناء إجراء العملية.